<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[My Little Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://laptite.github.io/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://laptite.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-06-26T17:57:51-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://laptite.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It gets better]]></title>
    <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/it-gets-better/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-26T16:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/it-gets-better</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="http://laptite.github.io/images/yessss.jpg" width="300" height="300" title="[Pixel Img]" >
We&rsquo;re closing in on the 4th week of Flatiron School and so far it&rsquo;s been great. I get up 10 minutes before my alarm clock every morning and I look forward to seeing my instructors and classmates. There are so many people in the class that I revel in learning something new about them every day. There are fun team-building exercises and plenty opportunities to get to know each other better &ndash; &ldquo;lunch! oh yes, lunch!&rdquo; But that&rsquo;s not the whole story.</p>

<p>The 12-week immersive program is definitely intense. I have to be honest, it&rsquo;s been a really trying few weeks for me. While there are 4-weeks of prework to complete, it hasn&rsquo;t prepared me for what was to come. Bear in mind that I walked into this as a non-programmer with a geeky techie penchant.</p>

<p>What I&rsquo;m learning, after interacting with other students, is that this type of course attracts many of a certain kind of person: the A-type.  So let me digress for a moment. What&rsquo;s an A-type person you ask? Well, in my interpretation we&rsquo;re looking at a set of a highly competitive, high strung, multi-tasking, impatient and workaholic types. Now let me ask you this. You take a whole bunch of people like this, put them in classroom and tell them not to compete against each other&hellip; and what do you get? You get a bunch of people gauging the rate of their learning against everyone else&rsquo;s, which translates to: [fingers spelling out &ldquo;L&rdquo; on my forehead].</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re all strongly encouraged not to do this. But do we do that? Of course not. We go home, cry on our pillows and wonder why we&rsquo;re such idiots (or maybe I&rsquo;m just speaking for myself). The funny thing is that every person I&rsquo;ve talked to claims to be the most behind in their learning. Seriously. We&rsquo;ve come to the point that we&rsquo;re even competing on who&rsquo;s the most behind. I think I&rsquo;ve made my point on personality type.</p>

<p>Anyway, what I&rsquo;ve learned through this process is that learning how to program is challenging for many reasons, few of which are technical. Given the time and the inclination, I believe that anyone who puts their mind to learning any topic will eventually learn it. The challenge of this program is entirely affected by one factor: time. Can you learn it fast enough?  This means battling your own ego on a daily basis, and learning how to deal with your frustrations.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to pretend that I woke up one morning and everything magically became easy peasy lemon squeezy. It&rsquo;s only week 4 and there&rsquo;s a long way to go. Things are gradually getting better mostly through my own efforts. So here are some key take-aways: take ownership of your learning status (did I do all the homework? did I suffer the blank screen glare until I found a solution, or did I ride someone else&rsquo;s coat tails?), stop comparing yourself against others (yeah, right), and chill the f*ck out (there are worse things that could be happening in your life). Savor those &ldquo;yessss&rdquo; moments when you figure out the most elementary things.  And remember that at the end of the day, it gets better&hellip; albeit incrementally.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn Ruby online]]></title>
    <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/learn-ruby-online/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-16T22:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/learn-ruby-online</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="http://laptite.github.io/images/term-ruby.jpg" width="375" height="281" title="[Skillshare pic]" ><br>
Source: Skillcrush</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m the kind of person that likes books with pictures. I also tend to learn best by observing and grasping patterns.  So lucky for me, there are a number of interactive Ruby learning tools available to suit different learning styles.  I haven&rsquo;t yet checked all of these out, so this post is part review and part reminder.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://tryruby.org">TryRuby</a></strong><br>
TryRuby is the most adorable browser-based learning tool ever. It&rsquo;s hosted by CodeSchool. I love the super-cute storybook layout and characters. I first tried this out about 6 months ago and while it was very easy to follow, I didn&rsquo;t really understand what I was doing or why. At the end of the module I didn&rsquo;t get the point of what I had just done. That said, TryRuby is so irresistible that you <em>will</em> start typing Ruby.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubykoans.com">RubyKoans</a></strong><br>
I love the concept of RubyKoans. It&rsquo;s not browser-based. Instead you download a folder of ruby files and you go onto to follow a &ldquo;path to enlightenment.&rdquo; Having already learned the basics of Ruby, I&rsquo;ve found this game to be very helpful in reinforcing what I&rsquo;ve already learned to-date. It&rsquo;s definitely helped me get a handle on some weaknesses.  I wouldn&rsquo;t recommend this to a complete programming newbie.  This learning tool requires some familiarity with both a text editor and your terminal.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.rubeque.com">Rubeque</a></strong><br>
I just heard about this one, and I really think this is going to help me hone my skills. Last week I didn&rsquo;t even know what an enumerable was, but this week I&rsquo;m ready to throw on the punching gloves! This browser-based tool gets you to &ldquo;hone your skills by solving small Ruby programs while competing against other Rubyists&rdquo;. Challenges are listed in a table, which you can filter by level of difficulty. Awesome. Did someone just turn on the music? It&rsquo;s the Eye of the Tiger, baby. Bring it on biznitch!</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/ryanb/ruby-warrior">Ruby warrior</a></strong>
While I fondly remember Adventure games of days gone by, I could never figure out what the heck word I was supposed to use to move forward. I sucked so bad at those games. This said I can&rsquo;t wait to try this one. Go to this git repo and get instructions on installing the gem and then it&rsquo;s off to the races. You&rsquo;re a warrior climbing a tall tower in search of a precious Ruby at the very top. To get to the next floor, you need to write Ruby script for the warrior to battle enemies, rescue captives, and reach the stairs. Sweet.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://hackety.com">Hackety Hack</a></strong><br>
All these interactive tools have me so spoiled. You watch video, a cute cartoon, compete against each other and role-play. As Tony the Tiger would say &ldquo;It&rsquo;s grrrrreat!&rdquo; So honestly Hackety Hack, what are you thinking making me read words? Plus, I have to install an application that takes space on my hard drive? I don&rsquo;t think so homey.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://railsforzombies.org">RailsforZombies</a></strong><br>
Classic learning tool by Codeschool to learn rails. Zombies and learning challenges: what more do you need? I&rsquo;d write more but I haven&rsquo;t finished it yet.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubymonk.com">RubyMonk</a></strong><br>
I haven&rsquo;t tried this one yet but if Ruby&rsquo;s creator Yukihiro Matsumoto says he likes it, well then I&rsquo;m just going to have to go ahead and try it.</p>

<p>Reference: <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/samnang/interactive-ruby-learning">https://speakerdeck.com/samnang/interactive-ruby-learning</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Prelude To Coding]]></title>
    <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/prelude-to-coding/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-09T00:00:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/09/prelude-to-coding</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>h&mdash;&ndash;
layout: post
title: &ldquo;Prelude to Coding&rdquo;
author: Alisa Chang
date: 2013-06-09 00:34
comments: true
published: true</p>

<h2>categories: [Adventure game, Musing]</h2>

<p><img class="left" src="http://laptite.github.io/images/Bored_20px.png" width="350" height="232" title="[Pixel Img]" ></p>

<div style="clear: both; font-family: Courier New">
$ emacs -batch -l dunnet
<br>
Dead end
You are at a dead end of a dirt road.  The road goes to the east.  In the distance you can see that it will eventually fork off.  The trees here are very tall royal palms, and they are spaced equidistant from each other.
There is a shovel here. 
</div>


<br>




<div style="font-family: Arial">
Every once or twice in a lifetime, you’re given this incredible gift:  The realization of a dead end, coupled with an opportunity to start over.  You might choose to ignore the chance and unhappily continue along the same old but ‘safe’ path.  But I won&#8217;t. Not me.  Not anymore.
</div>




<div style="font-family: Courier New">
> Take shovel <br>
Taken.<br>
> 
Go East <br>
E/W Dirt road <br>
You are on the continuation of a dirt road.  There are more trees on both sides of you.  The road continues to the east and west. There is a large boulder here.
</div>


<br>




<div style="font-family: Arial">
<p>There’s something to be said about wanting to make a change but not knowing what to do about it.  It&#8217;s called:  Not enough data.</p>

<p>Here&#8217;s what my life&#8217;s looked like in recent years:</p>

I used to want to become an animator. Maybe I should do that.</div>


<div style="font-family: Courier New">
>dig<br>
Digging here reveals nothing.
</div>


<br>


<div style="font-family: Arial">
I love to cook.  Maybe I should go to Culinary School.
</div>


<div style="font-family: Courier New">
>go west<br>
Dead end
</div>


<br>


<div style="font-family: Arial">
Hm. Maybe this job’s not so bad after all. 
</div>


<div style="font-family: Courier New">
>go north<br>
You can&#8217;t go that way.
</div>


<br>


<div style="font-family: Arial">
Plus I&#8217;m good at it&#8230;
</div>


<div style="font-family: Courier New">
>climb<br>
You manage to get about two feet up the tree and fall back down.  You notice that the tree is very unsteady.<br>
>damn it<br>
I don&#8217;t understand that.<br>
>screw you<br>
I don&#8217;t understand that.
</div>


<br>




<div style="font-family: Arial">
In the interim everyone around me keeps telling me to do what I love. Do what you love.  What does that mean?  I keep on my ‘safe’ path until&#8230;
</div>


<div style="font-family: Courier New">
You begin to shake a tree, and notice a coconut begin to fall from the air. As you try to get your hand up to block it, you feel the impact as it lands on your head. You are dead.<br>
You have scored 0 out of a possible 90 points.<br>
$
</div>


<br>


<div style="font-family: Arial">
<p>Some time after the coconut incident, it occurs to me that there&#8217;s always been one constant for happiness in my life: solving problems through applied technology. I dig it.  I geek out on it.  It&#8217;s my thing.</p>

<p>And this is sort of how I ended up at the Flatiron School.</p>

<p>I don’t think I’ll ever be done debugging my life.  But what I do know is that it feels great being at Flatiron.  I&#8217;m surrounded by awesome people that share an insatiable desire to learn. One week in, and it’s clear to us all that this is not your typical continuing-education course.  The new order of the day is to let go of all pretenses and free your inner nerd.  Like Avi said on Day 1:  Be open to learn and don’t be an asshole.</p>
</div>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Hello World]]></title>
    <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/05/hello-world/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-05T14:08:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/05/hello-world</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
