<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: newbie | My Little Blog]]></title>
  <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/categories/newbie/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://laptite.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2013-08-24T22:28:11-04:00</updated>
  <id>http://laptite.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Your Name]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Argh Matey: Connecting the dots in Rails]]></title>
    <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/07/10/argh/"/>
    <updated>2013-07-10T23:39:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/07/10/argh</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/argh.png" width="320" height="208" title="[Pixel Img]" >
It&rsquo;s been a crazy 5 weeks at the Flatiron School, but things are finally starting to click &ndash; thanks in part to our instructors patiently walking us through a number of examples. While this post might seem trivial to some readers, bear in mind that 5 weeks ago I had TextWrangler installed on my laptop. Ew. I know, like, for realz AND I was practicing stuff like var = x.</p>

<p>Anyway, fast forward to the future: the one exercise that resonated with me was one relating Pirates and Ships. It helped me understand Ruby at a time that I hit a seemingly bottomless pit of &lsquo;why the heck don&rsquo;t I get this stuff?&rsquo; desperation. Plus, it kept me entertained since every sentence invariably ended up with an &ldquo;argh matey&rdquo; in my head.</p>

<p>The good news is that after a few weeks of Ruby and a week of Sinatra, we&rsquo;ve started to delve into Rails. One benefit of learning Sinatra first is that you realize how magical Rails is. Holy Shit it does WHAT for you? Everything?! You just wave your magic wand and friggin' wha?! Ladies and Gentlemen [drumroll] et voilà [poof] ze app extraordinaire! [applause]</p>

<p>Not exactly.</p>

<p>The bad news is, we had homework due in which we were asked to populate a database and create a simple app based on a previous Sinatra application. How hard could that be? I mean Rails is freakin' magic after all. Ok, well maybe we also had to scrape data off a website first before.</p>

<p>So (staring down at my laptop) my first question is how do I get data in this thing? At this point, I should mention that until recently, accessing and entering data has been something of a mystery to me. Everyone&rsquo;s debugging and doing params stuff while I can&rsquo;t seem to select the right command in irb that does anything useful &ndash; driving blind at 150mph. Classic. We&rsquo;ll come back to that.</p>

<p>The first thing to grasp about Rails is that the framework is composed of three primary components the: Model, View and Controller. Note that the Model talks to the database using some Rails voodoo called ActiveRecord. I like this handy-dandy diagram because it shows you how the database interacts with the framework. But I hate this image because it confuses my thinking of where to enter my code so that it automagically pulls my data into the database. <img class="right" src="/images/mvc_github.png" width="453"></p>

<p>No worries. There must be some guide that explicitly states how to get your data in, so that you can figuratively link your model, views and controller right? Wrong. Someone tell me why there isn&rsquo;t such as resource within the top 3 search results! I&rsquo;ll tell you why&hellip; like duh, you just setup your models, and then your controller is a basic ruby class and then all you have to do is just populate your database and test it in your views. And if you&rsquo;re having trouble with the data, you just throw in pry-debugger or raise params. Capisce? [blank stare] No.</p>

<p>The first time I used Rails, I peeked into every folder trying to figure out the appropriate place for my database (see my Sublime sidebar below left). Now that I look at it, I feel like I should have been like: &ldquo;Duh, what about the db directory?&rdquo;</p>

<p><img class="left" src="/images/sidebar.png" width="222"></p>

<p>Let me break down my quandary for you. There are plenty search results for &lsquo;Rails database&rsquo; but the best answers show individual chunks of code without stating where it belongs. Some people talk about creating a controller and a model, others create just a model, there are examples on how to create a rake task in the lib directory, and others still enter their code in a seeds.rb file in the db directory. Everyone online has an opinion, and everyone&rsquo;s an expert.</p>

<p>BUT if you just want to play around with Rails to get a hang of it, here&rsquo;s how I recommend you get started once you&rsquo;ve installed Rails.</p>

<p><strong>Step 1 &ndash; Create a new rake application and cd into your application:</strong></p>

<pre><code>&gt; rails new pirates-rails-app
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Step 2 &ndash; Create two Models (notice that Model title names are always singular):</strong></p>

<pre><code>&gt; rails generate model Ship name:string pirate_id:integer
</code></pre>

<p>Follow the Rails convention of naming your components properly if you want your app to work properly. In this example we use column name and type, but you could omit this piece <code>[name:string pirate_id:integer]</code> and add whatever columns you like later.</p>

<p>You should have two new ruby class files in the Model directory.</p>

<pre><code>class Pirate &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
   attr_accessible :location, :name
end    

class Ship &lt; ActiveRecord::Base
   attr_accessible :name, :pirate_id
end
</code></pre>

<p><strong>Step 3 &ndash; Enter some data to play with in the seed.rb file, which is in the db directory:</strong></p>

<pre><code>ships = Ship.create([{ name: 'Queen Anne\'s Revenge', pirate_id: 1}, {name: 'Barnacle', pirate_id: 2}])
pirates = Pirate.create([{ location: 'West Indies', name: 'Blackbeard'}, { location: 'Rumrunner Isle', name: 'JackSparrow' }])
</code></pre>

<p>Enter &lsquo;rails console&rsquo; in the command line to launch Rails irb console. If you can get your data to pass muster here, it should work in the seeds file. This won&rsquo;t work until you run a &lsquo;rake db:migrate&rsquo; to migrate your data into the database. Hold off on this for a little while.</p>

<p><strong>Step 4 &ndash; The easiest way to create a Controller is to generate a scaffold. You&rsquo;ll probably hear all sorts of reasons why you should shun scaffolds, but it&rsquo;s a great way to see how things connect:</strong></p>

<pre><code>&gt; rails generate scaffold Ship
&gt; rails generate scaffold Pirate
</code></pre>

<p>Don&rsquo;t just accept this. Look at the code in the controller files to get a feel for why each block exists.</p>

<p><strong>Important!</strong> Notice that controllers are always plural. So be careful if you run &lsquo;rails generate controller pirate<strong>s</strong>&rsquo; instead of scaffold. Don&rsquo;t mess this one up either unless you want your app to break.</p>

<p><strong>Step 5 &ndash; Get in the sandbox and play with your localhost site:</strong></p>

<pre><code>&gt; rake db:migrate 
  # this migrates your tables to the database

&gt; rake server
  # this command will rackup a port for you to access your web app
  # "Starting Rack on port 4000" -&gt; http://localhost:4000/

&gt; rake routes 
  # this allows you to see what web app routes are available
</code></pre>

<p>The View files associated with your scaffold and routes are in the view folder. Check them out and add some HTML and some styling. There&rsquo;s a lot more to do, but I found this to be a good start to wrap my head around the concept of MVC and Rails.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[It gets better]]></title>
    <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/it-gets-better/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-26T16:05:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/26/it-gets-better</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img class="left" src="/images/yessss.jpg" width="300" height="300" title="[Pixel Img]" >
We&rsquo;re closing in on the 4th week of Flatiron School and so far it&rsquo;s been great. I get up 10 minutes before my alarm clock every morning and I look forward to seeing my instructors and classmates. There are so many people in the class that I revel in learning something new about them every day. There are fun team-building exercises and plenty opportunities to get to know each other better &ndash; &ldquo;lunch! oh yes, lunch!&rdquo; But that&rsquo;s not the whole story.</p>

<p>The 12-week immersive program is definitely intense. I have to be honest, it&rsquo;s been a really trying few weeks for me. While there are 4-weeks of prework to complete, it hasn&rsquo;t prepared me for what was to come. Bear in mind that I walked into this as a non-programmer with a geeky techie penchant.</p>

<p>What I&rsquo;m learning, after interacting with other students, is that this type of course attracts many of a certain kind of person: the A-type.  So let me digress for a moment. What&rsquo;s an A-type person you ask? Well, in my interpretation we&rsquo;re looking at a set of a highly competitive, high strung, multi-tasking, impatient and workaholic types. Now let me ask you this. You take a whole bunch of people like this, put them in classroom and tell them not to compete against each other&hellip; and what do you get? You get a bunch of people gauging the rate of their learning against everyone else&rsquo;s, which translates to: [fingers spelling out &ldquo;L&rdquo; on my forehead].</p>

<p>We&rsquo;re all strongly encouraged not to do this. But do we do that? Of course not. We go home, cry on our pillows and wonder why we&rsquo;re such idiots (or maybe I&rsquo;m just speaking for myself). The funny thing is that every person I&rsquo;ve talked to claims to be the most behind in their learning. Seriously. We&rsquo;ve come to the point that we&rsquo;re even competing on who&rsquo;s the most behind. I think I&rsquo;ve made my point on personality type.</p>

<p>Anyway, what I&rsquo;ve learned through this process is that learning how to program is challenging for many reasons, few of which are technical. Given the time and the inclination, I believe that anyone who puts their mind to learning any topic will eventually learn it. The challenge of this program is entirely affected by one factor: time. Can you learn it fast enough?  This means battling your own ego on a daily basis, and learning how to deal with your frustrations.</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m not going to pretend that I woke up one morning and everything magically became easy peasy lemon squeezy. It&rsquo;s only week 4 and there&rsquo;s a long way to go. Things are gradually getting better mostly through my own efforts. So here are some key take-aways: take ownership of your learning status (did I do all the homework? did I suffer the blank screen glare until I found a solution, or did I ride someone else&rsquo;s coat tails?), stop comparing yourself against others (yeah, right), and chill the f*ck out (there are worse things that could be happening in your life). Savor those &ldquo;yessss&rdquo; moments when you figure out the most elementary things.  And remember that at the end of the day, it gets better&hellip; albeit incrementally.</p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Learn Ruby online]]></title>
    <link href="http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/learn-ruby-online/"/>
    <updated>2013-06-16T22:23:00-04:00</updated>
    <id>http://laptite.github.io/blog/2013/06/16/learn-ruby-online</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p><img src="/images/term-ruby.jpg" width="375" height="281" title="[Skillshare pic]" ><br>
Source: Skillcrush</p>

<p>I&rsquo;m the kind of person that likes books with pictures. I also tend to learn best by observing and grasping patterns.  So lucky for me, there are a number of interactive Ruby learning tools available to suit different learning styles.  I haven&rsquo;t yet checked all of these out, so this post is part review and part reminder.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://tryruby.org">TryRuby</a></strong><br>
TryRuby is the most adorable browser-based learning tool ever. It&rsquo;s hosted by CodeSchool. I love the super-cute storybook layout and characters. I first tried this out about 6 months ago and while it was very easy to follow, I didn&rsquo;t really understand what I was doing or why. At the end of the module I didn&rsquo;t get the point of what I had just done. That said, TryRuby is so irresistible that you <em>will</em> start typing Ruby.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubykoans.com">RubyKoans</a></strong><br>
I love the concept of RubyKoans. It&rsquo;s not browser-based. Instead you download a folder of ruby files and you go onto to follow a &ldquo;path to enlightenment.&rdquo; Having already learned the basics of Ruby, I&rsquo;ve found this game to be very helpful in reinforcing what I&rsquo;ve already learned to-date. It&rsquo;s definitely helped me get a handle on some weaknesses.  I wouldn&rsquo;t recommend this to a complete programming newbie.  This learning tool requires some familiarity with both a text editor and your terminal.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://www.rubeque.com">Rubeque</a></strong><br>
I just heard about this one, and I really think this is going to help me hone my skills. Last week I didn&rsquo;t even know what an enumerable was, but this week I&rsquo;m ready to throw on the punching gloves! This browser-based tool gets you to &ldquo;hone your skills by solving small Ruby programs while competing against other Rubyists&rdquo;. Challenges are listed in a table, which you can filter by level of difficulty. Awesome. Did someone just turn on the music? It&rsquo;s the Eye of the Tiger, baby. Bring it on biznitch!</p>

<p><strong><a href="https://github.com/ryanb/ruby-warrior">Ruby warrior</a></strong>
While I fondly remember Adventure games of days gone by, I could never figure out what the heck word I was supposed to use to move forward. I sucked so bad at those games. This said I can&rsquo;t wait to try this one. Go to this git repo and get instructions on installing the gem and then it&rsquo;s off to the races. You&rsquo;re a warrior climbing a tall tower in search of a precious Ruby at the very top. To get to the next floor, you need to write Ruby script for the warrior to battle enemies, rescue captives, and reach the stairs. Sweet.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://hackety.com">Hackety Hack</a></strong><br>
All these interactive tools have me so spoiled. You watch video, a cute cartoon, compete against each other and role-play. As Tony the Tiger would say &ldquo;It&rsquo;s grrrrreat!&rdquo; So honestly Hackety Hack, what are you thinking making me read words? Plus, I have to install an application that takes space on my hard drive? I don&rsquo;t think so homey.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://railsforzombies.org">RailsforZombies</a></strong><br>
Classic learning tool by Codeschool to learn rails. Zombies and learning challenges: what more do you need? I&rsquo;d write more but I haven&rsquo;t finished it yet.</p>

<p><strong><a href="http://rubymonk.com">RubyMonk</a></strong><br>
I haven&rsquo;t tried this one yet but if Ruby&rsquo;s creator Yukihiro Matsumoto says he likes it, well then I&rsquo;m just going to have to go ahead and try it.</p>

<p>Reference: <a href="https://speakerdeck.com/samnang/interactive-ruby-learning">https://speakerdeck.com/samnang/interactive-ruby-learning</a></p>
]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
